Okay, בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is סנהדרין כ, Sanhedrin
chaf, סנהדרין Sanhedrin 20,
second line from the top. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amr Rabbi Yochanan, we're
in the middle of a section of אגדתא aggadata that started with
a discussion in the משנה mishna about a king marrying the widows
of the past king, and with דוד David and שאול, Shaul, and
that got to the discussion about דוד's David wives and מיכל Michal
and פלטי בן ליש Palti ben Laish who was married off, מיכל
Michal was married off to until she was then given to her
rightful husband דוד. David. So we continue with that. אמר רבי יוחנן,
Amr Rabbi Yochanan, what's meant by the פסוק pasuk רבות בנות עשו
חיל ואת עלית על כולנה? Rabos banos asu chayil v'at alis al
kulanu? Many daughters have done, have made valor, but you have risen
above all of them. רבות בנות עשו חיל, Rabos banos asu chayil,
זה יוסף ובועז, ze Yosef u'Boaz, that refers to, continuing the conversation
from yesterday, that refers to יוסף Yosef and בועז Boaz who were
able to withstand sexual temptation. But as the גמרא gemara discussed, it
was only for בועז Boaz only for a brief period of time,
for one night, and she was a single woman. And for יוסף,
Yosef, a married woman, and wasn't, but also, she wasn't lying together
in bed with him. ואת עלית על כולנה, V'at alis al kulanu,
זה פלטי בן ליש. ze Palti ben Laish. But you have surpassed
them all is פלטי בן ליש Palti ben Laish who was married
to מיכל Michal all those years and, according to the גמרא, gemara,
did not engage in sexual relations that entire time.
Very, of course, interesting and ironic that it's talking here about praising
women and it's focusing on the men in their resisting of sexual
temptation. Where's the discussion about מיכל Michal and her resisting of temptation?
Fascinating that that is absent here. Okay, אמר רבי יוחנן, Amr Rabbi
Yochanan, similarly said רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, what is meant, שקר החן
והבל היופי? sheker hachen v'hevel hayofi? שקר החן, Sheker hachen, זה יוסף.
ze Yosef. False is
charm is יוסף. Yosef. That was one thing, it was that she
wasn't even in bed with him, she was a married woman. והבל
היופי, V'hevel hayofi, זה בועז. ze Boaz. And it all looks very
nice, that's what בועז Boaz did, it's all nice, but that's not
really the real substance. יראת ה' היא תתהלל, Yiras Hashem hee tishallal,
what is truly fearful of God? זה פלטי בן ליש. ze Palti
ben Laish. Again פלטי בן ליש Palti ben Laish and again fascinating
taking a פסוק pasuk about women and focusing on the man of
that equation.
Okay, דבר אחר, davar acher, another interpretation. שקר החן, Sheker hachen, זה
דורו של משה, ze doro shel Moshe, והבל היופי, v'hevel hayofi, זה
דורו של יהושע. ze doro shel Yehoshua. Now we're going to be
talking again about men,
but now in terms of learning תורה. Torah. So the generation of
משה Moshe and the generation of יהושע, Yehoshua, that all looked very
nice, but it was ultimately, it wasn't the real deal, certainly not
as much as the last one we're about to say. יראת ה'
היא תתהלל, Yiras Hashem hee tishallal, זה דורו של חזקיה. ze doro
shel Chizkiya. This is the generation of
חזקיה Chizkiya where the גמרא gemara says that they checked from דן
Dan to באר שבע Be'er Sheva and there was like no עמי
הארץ amei ha'aretz and everybody was like, even the children knew tremendous
amount of תורה. Torah. So you can't compare it, so even though
משה Moshe and יהושע Yehoshua look great, we tend to romanticize those
times, but the real תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah really, really expanded under
חזקיה. Chizkiya. דבר אחר, Davar acher, שקר החן, sheker hachen, זה דורו
של משה ויהושע, ze doro shel Moshe v'Yehoshua, והבל היופי, v'hevel hayofi,
זה דורו של חזקיה. ze doro shel Chizkiya. So even including חזקיה
Chizkiya in the הבל היופי, hevel hayofi, so what's the real
accomplishment? יראת ה' היא תתהלל, Yiras Hashem hee tishallal, זה דורו של
רבי יהודה בר אלעאי. ze doro shel Rebbi Yehuda bar Ilai. That's
the generation of רבי יהודה בר אלעאי. Rebbi Yehuda bar Ilai. The
רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, the standard תנא. tanna. אמרו עליו על רבי
יהודה בר אלעאי, Amru alav al Rebbi Yehuda bar Ilai, שהיו ששה
תלמידים מתכסים בטלית אחת. shehayu shisha talmidim miskasim b'tallis achas. There were
six students that would cover themselves in one טלית, tallis, meaning that
they had no money, they couldn't even afford a blanket, six of
them had to share essentially a blanket or an outer garment and
ועוסקים בתורה, v'oskim b'Torah, nevertheless they would learn תורה. Torah. Which raises
an interesting question whether the point here is about the יראת השם,
yiras Hashem, יראת ה' היא תתהלל, yiras Hashem hee tishallal, and about
the מסירות נפש mesiras nefesh of תלמוד תורה, Talmud Torah, which is
definitely demonstrated by the רבי יהודה בר אלעאי Rebbi Yehuda bar Ilai
story,
but or whether it is about the degree to which תורה Torah
was known and was learned, which is different than the מסירות נפש
mesiras nefesh question. That seems to have been really throughout the גמרא
gemara seen as חזקיה Chizkiya was the epitome of that. One could
even say like nowadays as well,
probably not so much in terms of מסירות נפש mesiras nefesh for
תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah in terms of this type of thing about
poverty and dire straights and so on. I mean people obviously give
over in terms of their time and dedicate their lives, but not
like the story of רבי יהודה בר אלעאי. Rebbi Yehuda bar Ilai.
And but nevertheless, probably now, I can't exactly compare it to דורו
של חזקיה, doro shel Chizkiya, but bracketing דורו של חזקיה, doro shel
Chizkiya, there are more Jews studying תורה Torah and more ישיבות yeshivos
now than ever were before in recorded Jewish history, minus maybe the
דורו של חזקיה. doro shel Chizkiya. So it's a difference between the
degree of learning and the spread of learning and the knowledge of
learning and the מסירות נפש mesiras nefesh related to the learning. Okay,
so now we come, we turn to the next
משנה. mishna. מת לא מת, Mes lo mes, we're still on the
king. So we talked about a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol if somebody
dies and the פסוק pasuk about מן המקדש לא יצא min hamikdash
lo yeitzei and does that really mean he can't leave the בית
המקדש Beis hamikdash or does that mean that he has to not
be go together in... With the funeral procession, how about the king?
So there it's not a פסוק, pasuk, but it's things that we
are doing to sort of protect
and affirm the status of the king. So if an immediate relative
dies, אינו יוצא מפתח פלטרין שלו. eino yotzei mipetach paltarin shelo. He
does not leave the door of his castle, even if it's an
immediate relative, which is interesting. I guess his private mourning will take
place, but once he goes out, he has to be a public
figure and he cannot be a private individual in that context and
he is not allowed to accompany the funeral procession.
רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, אם רוצה לצאת אחר המטה יוצא.
im rotzeh latzeit achar hamitah yotzei. If he wants to, he's not
required to, but if he wants to, he can, שכן מצינו בדוד
שיצא אחר מיטתו. shekein matzinu beDovid sheyatza achar mitato. We find that
דוד Dovid followed the funeral bier of אבנר, Avner, who was the
general for שאול Shaul and had come over to דוד'ס Dovid's side,
but then יואב בן צרויה Yoav ben Tzeruya killed him with a
deception. שנאמר, Shene'emar, and it says, והמלך דוד הולך אחר המטה. veHamalech
Dovid holeich achar hamitah. דוד Dovid followed, the King דוד Dovid followed
the funeral bier
to really demonstrate public mourning for אבנר. Avner. אמרו לו, Amru lo,
so the חכמים chachamim said back to him, לא היה הדבר אלא
לפייס את העם. lo hayah hadavar ela lepayeis et ha'am. No, that
was a special exception. He needed to appease the people. People thought
that maybe דוד Dovid had a hand in this. אבנר Avner was
going to help bring over all of ישראל Yisrael in order to
back
דוד'ס Dovid's realm when איש בשת, Ishboshet, שאול'ס Shaul's son,
had taken over שאול'ס Shaul's kingship. So here this really was risking
the
entire ascension of דוד Dovid to the kingship, and people might have
suspected him of being part of this plot. So that's why he
did it and it was a special exception. Similar to the discussion
before where רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda brings up a proof from a
פסוק, pasuk, and there was a response. In the משנה Mishnah before
there wasn't a response, but it was quoted in the גמרא Gemara
about the נשי המלך. n'shei hamalech. Does that mean the wives, or
does it mean your wives, and so on? The daughters of the
king in that context, and here the response was it was a
special exception. אמרו לו לא היה הדבר אלא לפייס את העם. Amru
lo lo hayah hadavar ela lepayeis et ha'am. וכשמברין אותו, Ukeshemavrin oso,
and when they give
him the meal that you give אבלים aveilim that the consolers feed
the אבל, aveil, כל העם מסובין על הארץ והוא מיסב על הדרגש.
kol ha'am mesubin al ha'aretz vehu meiseiv al hadargash. All of the
people recline on the ground and he reclines on the הדרגש. hadargash.
And in the גמרא Gemara we'll see what the הדרגש hadargash is,
similar to what we said by the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. There
we said the ספסל. safsal. So even though he is the mourner
and he is not sitting on a normal chair and he's close
to the ground because of the elevated status, the consolers are actually
directly on the ground. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, the גמרא. Gemara. Our
rabbis taught: מקום שנהגו נשים לצאת אחר המטה יוצאות
לפני המטה יוצאות. Makom shenahagu nashim latzeit achar hamitah yotzot lifnei hamitah
yotzot. Where the place where the practice was for women to go
behind
the coffin and the men would go in front, follow that practice.
And if the practice was for the women to go in front
and the men to go in back, then that would be the
practice you would follow.
רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, לעולם נשים לפני המטה יוצאות. le'olam
nashim lifnei hamitah yotzot. Women always would go in front of the
coffin, שכן מצינו בדוד שיצא אחר מיטתו של אבנר, shekein matzinu beDovid
sheyatza achar mitato shel Avner, because we find that דוד Dovid was
behind the coffin in the funeral procession when, and which means that
the women would have been in front because he was obviously with
the men. שנאמר, Shene'emar, as the פסוק pasuk says, והמלך דוד הולך
אחר המטה. veHamalech Dovid holeich achar hamitah. He went after, he followed
the coffin. אמרו לו, Amru lo, so they said to him, לא
היה הדבר אלא לפייס את העם. lo hayah hadavar ela lepayeis et
ha'am. Similar to the explanation in the משנה, Mishnah, except here it's
not a question of what is the king permissible to do, but
whether you can infer from what דוד Dovid did to a general
rule. Here the general rule would be how the men and women
would be divided and separated,
and the rabbis are saying again this was an exception, you can't
prove anything from there. But the exception wasn't that it was an
exception that the men were going in the back, but the point
was that the גמרא'ס Gemara's going to say even the women could
have been going in the back because דוד Dovid was actually mixing
with the mourners in the front and the back, the men and
the women, in order that everybody should see that he was mourning
for the death of אבנר. Avner. לפייס את העם
נתפייסו. Lefayeis et ha'am nispaisu. And then he succeeded in doing that
and in appeasing them.
שהיה דוד יוצא מבין האנשים ונכנס לבין הנשים יוצא מבין הנשים ונכנס
לבין האנשים. Shehayah Dovid yotzei mibein ha'anashim venichnas lebein hanashim yotzei mibein
hanashim venichnas lebein ha'anashim. He would be amongst the male mourners, whether
they were in the front or the back, and then go with
the women and then mix with them wherever they were and then
go back to the men and so on. So you can't prove
from there whether the men or the women were in the front
or the back. שנאמר, Shene'emar, as the פסוק pasuk says, וידעו כל
העם וכל ישראל כי לא הייתה מהמלך להמית את אבנר. vayedu kol
ha'am vechol Yisrael ki lo hayta mehamelech lehamis et Avner. And that's
how you know that he was successful because it says after he
did this and he gave a whole eulogy for אבנר Avner that
the people knew and they saw that he was not part of
the plot. So that's in terms of whether the men or the
women go, who goes in front, who goes in back, and the
חכמים chachamim are saying it really. is whatever the practice is. The
issue the concern here would be whether it is a concern that
if the women are in the front then the men are looking
at the women or are we saying that in time of mourning
that is not a concern that we should be having.
So and everybody agrees that it is acceptable if that is the
practice for women to go in front as well. Okay. דרש
רבא. Darash Rava. רבא Rava explicated. מאי דכתיב? Mai dichtiv? What is
meant by the
פסוק? pasuk? ויבאו כל העם להברות את דוד. Vayavo kol ha'am lehavrot
et David. The entire people came to do the סעודת הבראה seudat
havra'ah to give the consoling to דוד, David, feed דוד David in
the consoling that was done for mourners. כתיב להכרות וקרינן להברות. Ktiv
le'achrot vekarinan lehavrot. So it is written with a כ, chaf, להכרות,
le'achrot, to destroy, to cut them, but we read it להברות lehavrot
to give this mourner's meal. Now actually it is not written להכרות,
le'achrot, it is written להברות, lehavrot, but maybe you can say that
the word להברות lehavrot echoes the idea of להכרות. le'achrot. It could
have been written להכרות. le'achrot. It is almost the same word. And
that is to suggest the following. בתחילה להכרותו, Batchila le'achroto, and originally
they came to cut him down, to destroy him, they thought he
was part of the plot, ולבסוף להברותו, ule'vasof lehavroto, but in the
end after they saw how he practiced during the mourning and so
on, they came to do the normal consoling of the mourners and
the giving of the meal to the mourners. אמר רב יהודה אמר
רב, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav, said רב יהודה Rav Yehuda in
the name of רב. Rav. מפני מה נענש אבנר? Mipnei ma ne'enash
Avner? Why was אבנר Avner punished? Why did why I mean that
is always the question about בחירה חופשית bechirah chofshit and God's role
within this world. But אבנר Avner was not necessarily punished. He was
treacherously killed by יואב. Yoav. But okay, but still there has to
be justice. So what did he do to deserve this? Why was
he punished? מפני שהיה לו למחות בשאול ולא מיחה. Mipnei shehayah lo
limchot beShaul velo michah. He should have opposed שאול Shaul and he
did not oppose him. This is when שאול Shaul killed out נוב
עיר כהנים. Nov Ir Kohanim. He was in a position to speak
up. He was
and he was silent, so that idea of being like a bystander
and the responsibility of bystanders, the גמרא Gemara is very, very clear
about that in multiple places. He could have spoken up. רב יצחק
אמר מיחה. Rabbi Yitzchak amar michah. No, he did speak up, ולא
נענה, velo ne'enah, but he was not answered, meaning it did not
do any good. He tried to protest, but he was not successful.
So according to him, you will have to understand why he was
punished. But he wants to make it clear that אבנר Avner did
speak up. ושניהם מקרא אחד דרשו, Vesheneihem mikra echad darshu, and they
both are basing themselves on the same פסוק. pasuk. ויקונן המלך אל
אבנר ויאמר, Vayikonen hamelech el Avner vayomar, and the king דוד David
eulogized over אבנר, Avner, wailed over אבנר Avner and said, הכמות נבל
ימות אבנר? Hakemot naval yamut Avner? Will אבנר Avner die like the
death of a degenerate person?
ידיך לא אסורות ורגליך לא לנחשתים הוגשו. Yadecha lo asurot raglecha lo
linchoshtayim hugashu. Your hands were not bound, your feet were not put
into chains, and you just died out of treachery. It was a,
and how can this be? How can this terrible thing be that
you died in this disgraceful way? מאן דאמר לא מיחה, Man de'amar
lo michah, the one that says he did not protest, הכי קאמר,
hachi kamar, this is what דוד David is
saying. ידיך לא אסורות ורגליך לא לנחשתים הוגשו. Yadecha lo asurot raglecha
lo linchoshtayim hugashu. Look, you were not being silenced, your hands were
not bound, your feet were not in chains, nobody was stopping you,
you had the ability to speak up when שאול Shaul was doing
this. מאי טעמא לא מחית? Mai ta'ama lo machita? Why did you
not oppose? Why did you not speak up? כנפול לפני בני עולה
נפלת. Kinfol lifnei bnei avla nafaltah. And that is why you fell
as one would fall down by those who deal treacherously. Or maybe
that also means that you fell down in the presence of שאול
Shaul who was acting treacherously and you did not speak up. So
really, rather than be sort of reading דוד's David eulogy here as
saying this is so unjust and it was so unfitting of you
and so on, here it is saying this is why it happened,
you had nobody was holding you back, you should have spoken up.
ומאן דאמר מיחה, Uman de'amar michah, the one that says that he
did protest, ולא נענה, velo ne'enah, אתמוהי מתמה. itmuhei mitamei. So the
one that says he did and he was not answered, so דוד
David was actually astounded, not explaining that this is why it was
just, but the פשט pshat of the פסוק, pasuk, astounded at the
injustice of אבנר's Avner death. הכמות נבל ימות? Hakemot naval yamut? Should
you die the death of like
of a degenerate? ידיך לא אסורות ורגליך לא לנחשתים. Yadecha lo asurot
raglecha lo linchoshtayim. Your hands were not bound and your feet were
not in chains, meaning you acted, מכדי מחויי מחית. michtei machuya machita.
You acted, you did, your hands were free, your legs were free,
you stood up, you acted as you should have acted. מאי טעמא
כנפול לפני בני עולה
נפלת? Mai ta'ama kinfol lifnei bnei avla nafaltah? How could it be
that you fell in front of like the fall of falling in
front of the treacherous ones? So how could it be that you
suffered this terrible death? You did everything, you lived such a righteous
life.
Now, the גמרא Gemara says, למאן דאמר מיכה מאי טעמא יענש. leman
d’amar Micha mai ta’ama ye’anesh. Okay, so if he did protest Saul’s
wiping out of נוב עיר כהנים, Nov Ir Kohanim, why was he
punished? אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק ששהה מלכות בית דוד שתי שנים
ומחצה Amar Rav Nachman Bar Yitzchak shesha’ah malchus beis Dovid shtei shanim
u’mechtza because he sided with מפיבושת Mephibosheth for two and a half
years, and those two and a half years were time that דוד
Dovid should have become king, and he was on the wrong side
and he postponed דוד'ס מלכות Dovid’s malchus for two and a half
years. רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot have a whole discussion because there
were seven and a half years from the death of שאול Shaul
till דוד Dovid took over the kingship. So what’s the two and
a half years of the מפיבושת Mephibosheth rule right after שאול Shaul
and then there was a five-year gap or was there a five-year
gap and then it was two and a half years of מפיבושת?
Mephibosheth? But either way, you know, you supported מפיבושת Mephibosheth when you
should have supported דוד. Dovid.
Okay, moving on. וכשמברינוהו, Uchesh’mavrinoso, and then when you give him this
meal, you give it to him, everybody’s on the floor and he’s
on this
דרגש. dargash. So מאי דרגש? mai dargash? אמר עולא ערסא דגדא. Amar
Ulla arsa degada. It is a bed of
luck, the way רש״י Rashi explains, גד, gad, like גד גדי, gad
gadi, העורכים לגד שולחן, ha’orchim legad shulchan, you have in תנ״ך, Tanakh,
those that it’s some type of a sense of whether it was
a god or whether it was a sense of for luck and
for fortune.
And what this means is, you know, it would be a type
of a bed that would be laid out, sort of like כסא
של אליהו, kisei shel Eliyahu, כסא של אליהו, kisei shel Eliyahu, nobody
would sit on it, it would be there for display, it would
be considered to bring like good luck or good fortune to the
house. Okay, אמרו ליה
רבנן לעולא, Amru leh rabbanan le’Ulla, so that’s what he would, presumably
would be low enough and appropriate enough for a mourner to sit
on. So אמרו ליה רבנן לעולא מי איכא מידי דעד האידנא לא
אותביניה והשתא מותבינן ליה? Amru leh rabbanan le’Ulla mi ika midei d’ad
ha’idna lo oshvinei v’hashta moshvinei leh? Is there, would that make any
sense that something, you know, nobody sat, ever sat on this bed
and it’s just there as decoration and now, you know,
it’s appropriate to sit on it? Like that doesn’t make sense, you’d
sort of say you should sit on something that’s a different type
of a seat, but something that’s really decoration, like what’s the significance
of sitting on something, you know, that’s not even really made for
sitting? So מתקיף לה רבא מאי
קושיא? matkif leh Rava mai kushya? Why is that a problem? דילמא
מידי דהוה אאכילה ושתיה. Dilma midei d’hava achila ushtiya.
Maybe it’s just like we, you know, everything is different for an
אבל, avel, like when it comes to eating and drinking, דעד האידנא
לא
אכליניה ולא אשקיניה השתא קא מאכלינן ליה וקא משקינן ליה d’ad ha’idna
lo achlinei v’lo ashkinei hashta ka machlinei leh v’ka mashkinei leh
and the סעודת הבראה seudos havra’ah that the מנחמים, menachamim, you know,
the consolers are the ones that feed him. So we do things
differently, so maybe I don’t know, it shows a topsy-turvy world, who
knows what? The fact that you don’t normally sit on this type
of a thing is not a reason to imagine that it couldn’t
be, you know, we couldn’t be doing it. It still wouldn’t exactly
explain why for a king and what’s the significance, but okay. So
the גמרא Gemara will continue. אלא אי קשיא הא קשיא. Ela i
kashya ha kashya. If there’s something that challenges this idea that your
דרגש dargash is this decorative bed, here’s the question. דרגש אינו צריך
לכפותו אלא זוקפו. Dargash eino tzarich lichfoso ela zokfo.
We taught in a ברייתא baraita that a דרגש, dargash, you know,
you don’t have to upturn it upside down, which is what the
גמרא Gemara would do, said you do as an אבל. avel. An
אבל avel the beds were turned upside down, nowadays we don’t do
that, somehow the covering of the mirrors is supposed to correspond to
that, can discuss that when we do מועד קטן. Moed Katan. But
anyway,
but what you do is you can stand it on its head,
so you know, you can sort of as opposed to it standing
on its legs, you tilt it ninety degrees and you stand it
lengthwise on its head. ואי סלקא דעתך ערסא דגדא אמאי אינו צריך
לכפותו? V’isalka daitach arsa degada amai eino tzarich lichfoso? But if it’s
just like a normal type of a bed, a decorative bed, why
wouldn’t you turn it over?
והתניא, V’hatanya, we taught in the ברייתא, baraita, הכופה מטתו לא מטתו
בלבד הוא כופה אלא כל מטות שיש בתוך ביתו כופה. hachofes mittaso
lo mittaso bilvad hu kofes ela kol mittos sheyesh b’soch beiso kofes.
So it’s not just his bed, but all the beds in the
house. So the גמרא Gemara says, so why wouldn’t you turn it
over if it’s this decorative bed? So גמרא Gemara says, that’s not
a question. מאי קושיא דילמא מידי דהוה אמטה המיוחדת לכלים? Mai kushya
dilma midei d’hava amitta hamyuchedes lekeilim? Maybe a bed not made for
sitting you don’t have to turn over, like we teach by a
bed that’s designated for כלים, keilim, like a type of something that’s
again, I don’t know why it’s called a bed, but it’s a
bed that basically you use as a chest and you know, you
store your pots and pans there, whatever you put there, maybe you
put nice things to display them on the bed. Okay, but it’s
not made for sleeping, and that bed you don’t turn over. דקתני,
D’katani, we teach, אם היתה מיוחדת לכלים אינו צריך לכפותו. im haysa
myuchedes lekeilim eino tzarich lichfoso. That if it’s designated for כלים, keilim,
you don’t have to turn it over. So similarly, this bed that’s
made to be decorative, you wouldn’t turn it over. So so far,
everything is consistent. Could be it's decorative, nevertheless an אבל avel sits
on it, or at least the king sits on it if that's
the most appropriate thing for a king, and you don't have to
turn it upside down because it's made to be decorative, okay, but
you still do something with it, so you stand it on its
head. אלא, ela, but we're still not satisfied that this is what
this דרגש dargash is. אי קשיא הא קשיא, i kashya ha kashya,
something is difficult, it's the following. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel omer, דרגש מתיר קרביטין והוא נופל מאליו, dargash matir
karbitin v'hu nofel me'elav, that what you do for a דרגש dargash
is you, rather than having to turn it upside down, you can
just undo the straps and it will fall on its own accord.
So it sounds like it's basically some type of a bed or
chair that the seat or the mattress or whatever is is held
up by straps, and he says just undo the straps and that's
like turning it upside down. ואי סלקא דעתך v'isalka daitach ערסא דגדא,
arsa d'gada, and if it's a normal like decorative bed, but a
classic bed, קרביטי מי איכא, karbiti mi ika, that doesn't have straps.
So clearly we're talking about something that is different. It's not just
a normal bed, but it's made like in a decorative way for
not sitting. So אלא, ela, so we have to figure out exactly
what this דרגש dargash is. So אלא כי אתא רבין אמר אמר
לי אומר רבנן, ela ki ata Ravin amar amar li omer rabanan,
one of the, when Ravin came from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael he
said one of the rabbis said to me, ורב תחליפא שמיה, v'Rav
Tachlifa shmey, his name was Rav Tachlifa, דשכיח בשוקא דגילדאי, d'shchiach b'shuka
d'gilda'ei, that he was very, he spent a lot of time in
the marketplace of the tanners, of the leather workers. ואמר לה, v'amar
leh, and they said to him, you know, מאי דרגש, mai dargash,
whatever, ערסא דצלא. arsa d'tzala. What is a דרגש? dargash? It is
a bed of leather. Meaning it is a bed where the mattress,
the the thing that you would actually lie on would be a
leather hide and that you would strap it to the frame of
the bed. Okay, and that would be what this is. Now how's
that going to explain why we're not going to turn it upside
down? Okay, so the reason is that as Rashi explains, that because
it does not have poles that extend beyond the height of the
leather. It's just a frame and then the leather is strapped onto
the frame at the exact height of the top of the bed.
So if you were to turn it upside down, the leather would
go against the floor and you would ruin the nice leather. And
that's why it says you don't turn it upside down, but you
just turn it on its head because we don't want you to
have to ruin your bed. And that's why רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says you don't have to do that, you
can just release the straps and you're sort of like undoing the
bed in that way. Okay. אמר רבי ירמיה אמר רבי יוחנן, amar
Rabbi Yirmiyah amar Rabbi Yochanan, דרגש סירוגו מתוכו. dargash sirugo mitocho.
Now we're going to explain how it's different besides that it has
a leather sort of, I don't know what to call it, a
mattress, but anyway surface. There the ways the straps are done is
different. A דרגש dargash you tie it from within it, meaning that
you insert the straps into holes that are within the legs and
then you make a knot there to hold them through, but the
straps of the leather go through holes that are in the frame
or in the leg.
Okay. מיטה סירוגה מעל גבה, mita siruga me'al gabah, but a bed,
which is really the way that they would sort of have the
surface of a normal bed is it would be a crisscrossing of
ropes and then you would put on that the mattress or the
hay or whatever you would put on it. So what, so that
would actually not be through holes that were in the frame, but
through, you would wrap the ropes around the frame. Okay, so they'd
be on the outside of the frame wrapped around and not going
through a hole in the frame. מעל גבה. me'al gabah.
So that's that's a difference besides that one is a crisscross of
ropes to put something on and the other is a piece of
leather that is being that that is serving as the surface. מיתיבי,
meiseiv, I'll challenge this.
You know, we taught in the mishna, כלי עץ מאימת מקבלים טומאה,
kli eitz me'eimas mikablim tumah,
when do wood vessels become tamei, when they are done with being
their גמר עבודה. gmar avodah. So when is that?
גמר מלאכה. gmar melacha. המיטה והעריסה, hamita v'ha'arisa, bed and an עריסה
arisa like also the couch that that we're talking about is the
עריסה, arisa, משישופם בעור הדג, misheyishofem b'or hadag,
when you smooth them over, they would use the the skin of
a fish to, like we would use sandpaper or whatever to buff
it to smooth it over, so the wood would have a nice
smooth finish. All right, so fine, that's when you know that you're
that it's done. ואם מיטה מסורגת מעל גבה למה לי שיפת עור
הדג, v'im mita mesoreget me'al gabah lama li shiphat or hadag, and
if but if you're wrapping the ropes around the outside of the
frame, so then nobody is looking at the frame, the frame is
is totally covered. The wood would have a nice smooth finish. All
right? So fine. That's when you know that it's done. ואי מטה
מסורגת מעל גבה v'ee mita mesoreghet me'al gabba למה לי שיפת עור
הדג? lama li shifat or hadag? And if but if you're wrapping
the ropes around the outside of the frame, so then nobody is
looking at the frame. The frame is totally covered up with the
ropes. So you know you only bother making a nice finish for
the visible surface. So obviously that can't be right.
So אלא חדה מתוכה. ela hada mittocha. Fine, you're right. Both of
them, it's so funny like why didn't they just look at what
they were talking about? I guess they were trying to figure out
what it was in the משנה Mishnah that was not the reality
that they were dealing with in בבל. Bavel. Okay, fine. So both
this
דרגש dargash and this, you know,
מיטה mita are the ropes go through the holes in the frame.
מיטה עולי ואפוקי בביזיוני, mita ooli v'afookei bivizyonei, דרגש עולי ואפוקי באפקסא.
dargash ooli v'afookei b'afkasa. However, the difference is the following: that in
a bed it goes in and out, you know, through the holes.
Okay? So maybe it was even like one rope that you would,
you know, sort of like think about like the eyelets in your
shoe, you know how you go back and forth and crisscross or
whatever? So there'd be holes along the frame
and there could even be one rope that they would both that
did the vertical and one rope the horizontal, and they would go
through the holes to make the whole horizontal and then back and
forth through the holes to make the whole vertical. Okay, that's what
it would be, through the holes, בביזיוני, bivizyonei, but the
דרגש, dargash, it is things that you would tie, you know,
באפקסא, b'afkasa, which is what do you call it, loops, no that's
the word, rings. So
you would tie the straps to external rings that would be held
into that were coming off of the frame. Okay. אמר רב יעקב
אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי הלכה כרבן שמעון בן גמליאל Amar Rav
Yaakov amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi halacha k'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel that
you don't have to upend this דרגש, dargash, you can just release
the straps. אמר רב יצחק בר אמי מיטה שנקליטיה יוצאין זוקפה ודייה.
Amar Rav Yitzchak bar Ami mita shenakliteha yotzin zokfa v'daya.
If you have a bed
that the posts go up high, if you would sometimes you would
have in the middle of the headboard and in the middle of
the footboard two tall posts and that then you could use and
put a cross beam across them and then put down a blanket
and it would be like a canopy, you know, or like a
cover, a sheet. So anyway, but you have these posts that go
up from the middle of the bed very high. So if you
were to turn the bed upside down, the bed would still be
very high off the ground. You wouldn't achieve the value of
כפיית המיטה. kefiyat hamita. So what you do is you do like
we were suggesting by the דרגש: dargash: you put it on its
head and you turn it up 90 degrees and that's what you
do. Okay, so that was the end of that just to figure
out this דרגש dargash of the כהן גדול. kohen gadol. Next משנה,
Mishnah, continuing excuse me of the king, of the מלך. melech. Next
משנה Mishnah continuing with the king: ומוציא למלחמת הרשות על פי בית
דין של שבעים ואחד. umotzi l'milchemet hareshut al pi beit din shel
shivim v'echad.
The king could take the people out for an optional war, meaning
a war of expansion, not a war of self-defense or of conquering
ישראל, Yisrael, but that you would need the consensus of the people
represented by the permission of the בית דין beit din of 71,
which he also taught in the first משנה. Mishnah. ופורץ לעשות לו
דרך ואין ממחין בידו uforetz laasot lo derech v'ein mamchin b'yado
and you break through other people's fences and yards if he needs
a path and nobody can stop him. Now, it's actually interesting because
often the I think the image is that that means let's say
the king is coming into town and he needs to get to
through somewhere or he's on the move, you would so you basically
make a path for him sort of like, you know, when they
have the police cars accompanying the president or something and it doesn't
matter, they just go through traffic, they go anywhere they want. That's
sort of what you might have imagined it, but if you look
at רש״י, Rashi, רש״י Rashi says לעשות לו דרך לשדהו ולכרמו. laasot
lo derech l'sadehu u'l'charmo.
So
it's actually not that he's traveling somewhere, but access to his fields,
like in a more private capacity, which is a little strange. Maybe
they know that because then he's not so much acting
in his king capacity, he's acting as a private field landowner. So
I don't exactly get that רש״י. Rashi. דרך המלך אין
לו שיעור. derech hamelech ein lo shiur. Now, the way of the
king has no size. You can however wide he needs it, you
make it, he has the right to pass through. וכל העם בוזזין
ונותנין לו v'chol ha'am bozezin v'notnin lo the whole people when they
despoil, if you take an army and you conquer and you take
the spoils, so they give him והוא נוטל חלק בראש v'hu notel
chelek b'rosh and he gets the first choice of the spoils, you
know, very much sort of reflecting realities at the time of
תנ״ך. Tanakh. I don't even think it was realities at the time
of the משנה. Mishnah. Okay. And רש״י Rashi adds ונוטל מחלק יפה
בראשון v'notel mechilek yafeh b'rishon
he gets the first choice ונוטל מחצה v'notel mechtza and he gets
half. So it's saying addition there which we'll see in the גמרא.
Gemara. Okay, גמרא: Gemara: תנינא חדא זימנא. tanina chada zimna. We already
taught in a once in the very first משנה Mishnah of this
מסכת masechet the idea that you need 71.
You know we learned before you also would need the אורים ותומים
Urim VeTumim and the משוח מלחמה. Mashuach Milchama. Fine. So
we already taught this before. So the גמרא Gemara says, איידי
דתני כל מילי דמלך תני נמי אין
מוציאין למלחמת הרשות.
Aidi detani kol milei d'melech tani nami
ein motzi'in lemilchemet hareshut.
You're right. Okay. But since we're here in this פרק Perek talking
about כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and מלך Melech and now we're discussing
the details of מלך, Melech, we also want to tie it back
and throw in this aspect about taking out to war. Okay. אמר
רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, said רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, now we get to
a very famous debate in the גמרא. Gemara. כל האמור בפרשת מלך
מלך מותר בו. Kol ha'amur b'parshas melech melech mutar bo. Everything that
it says in the פרשה Parsha of the king, you know when
שמואל, Shmuel, the people say that tell שמואל Shmuel that they want
a king and he's very offended, and אותי מאסת, Osi ma'astah, you
know what, you despised me and now you want a מלך. Melech.
It's not good enough that you have a נביא Navi and God
and a שופט, Shofet, right? And that gets to the whole question
in the תורה, Torah, you know, you'll say אשימה עלי מלך ככל
הגוים אשר סביבתי. Asimah alai melech kechol hagoyim asher sevivosai. You'll say
I want to put a king on me like all the nations.
Is it a מצוה Mitzvah to have a king? Is the תורה
Torah permitting it? What's that ככל הגוים? Kechol hagoyim? Doesn't sound like
it's necessarily the ideal. We know that certainly שמואל Shmuel was very
offended that the people wanted a king. On the other hand, a
theme very much, you know, in the שופטים Shoftim is בימים ההם
אין מלך בישראל איש הישר בעיניו יעשה. Bayamim haheim ein melech b'Yisrael
ish hayashar be'einav ya'aseh.
So fine. So when they do ask שמואל Shmuel for a king,
he tells them here's what the king can do: he can take
your, you know, your, he can take your daughters, he can take
your, your boys for, you know, for, to conscript them, he can
take your fields, he can do all these types of things, he'll
have this absolute power. So is that really true? Are those really
the powers of a king? So let's take a look. So אמר
רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, said רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, כל האמור בפרשת מלך
מלך מותר בו. Kol ha'amur b'parshas melech melech mutar bo. Yes, that
is the powers of the king. You know, he can do, he
has the right to, to take people, property, all of that.
רב Rav אמר, amar, רב Rav said, לא נאמרה פרשה זו אלא
לאיימם
עליהם. Lo ne'emra parsha zu ela l'ayem aleihem.
No,
this was only said to fear them. Now if you look at
רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says, אלא לאיימם עליהם שתהא אימת מלכים עליהם
אבל אינו מותר לעשות. Ela l'ayem aleihem shetehei eimas melachim aleihem aval
einu mutar la'asos. That they should be afraid of what he can
do, but he really doesn't have that power, right? That's the whole
problem if somebody calls your bluff. Okay, but the people should think
he has the power so that there should be the fear of
the king. Of course you could have said that, you know, it's
there in order that to get them to be afraid of having
a king and to change their mind about having a king, but
that's not what רש"י Rashi says.
I mean the end of that פרשה Parsha actually says, and here
I'm reading from שמואל א' ח', Shmuel Aleph Ches,
you know, where is it, פסוק י"ט, Pasuk Yud Tes,
I'll just read one פסוק Pasuk before that. צאנכם יעשר ואתם תהיו
לו לעבדים, Tzonchem ya'asor v'atem tihyu lo l'avadim,
he'll take tithes of your sheep and you'll be slaves to him.
וזעקתם ביום ההוא מלפני מלככם אשר בחרתם לכם, Uzakatem bayom hahu milifnei
malkechem asher bechartem lachem, you'll cry out on that day for cause
of your king and his power אשר בחרתם לכם asher bechartem lachem
that you have chosen. Notice you have chosen, you want it. ולא
יענה ה' אתכם ביום ההוא, V'lo ya'aneh Hashem eschem bayom hahu, and
ה' Hashem won't answer you. וימאנו העם לשמוע בקול שמואל, Vayema'anu ha'am
lishmo'a b'kol Shmuel, the people refused to listen to שמואל, Shmuel, ויאמרו
לא כי אם מלך יהיה עלינו. Vayomru lo ki im melech yihiyeh
aleinu. No,
we don't care that you're telling us it will be terrible, we
want a king. והיינו גם אנחנו ככל הגוים, V'hayinu gam anachnu kechol
hagoyim, and we'll be like all the other nations exactly like echoing,
you know, the פסוק Pasuk in the תורה. Torah. ושפטנו מלכנו ויצא
לפנינו ונלחם מלחמותינו. Ushfatanu malkeinu v'yatza l'faneinu v'nilcham milchamoseinu. וישמע שמואל את
דברי העם וידברם באזני ה'. Vayishma Shmuel es divrei ha'am vayidabrem b'oznei
Hashem. Okay.
So I would have said לאיימם עליהם L'ayem aleihem meant he wanted
them to change their mind. It's very clear from the פסוקים Pesukim
that that's what it is, because after he says the whole thing
it says that the people refused to listen to him. But רש"י
Rashi says it's in order that there would be אימת מלך עליהם
Eimas melech aleihem when they would have a king. All right. So
anyway, but it's not that technically he has those rights. תנאי. Tanna'ei.
The גמרא Gemara says this is like a debate of תנאים. Tannaim.
רבי יוסי אומר כל האמור בפרשת מלך מלך מותר בו, Rabbi Yose
omer kol ha'amur b'parshas melech melech mutar bo, like שמואל, Shmuel, anything
that's said in the king, the king is permitted to do. רבי
יהודה אומר לא נאמרה פרשה זו אלא כדי לאיימם עליהם שנאמר שום
תשים עליך מלך שתהא אימתו עליך. Rabbi Yehuda omer lo ne'emra parsha
zu ela k'dei l'ayem aleihem shene'emar som tasim alecha melech shetehei eimaso
alecha. So you know this is where רש"י Rashi was getting it
from, but again not פשט Peshat of the פסוקים Pesukim in שמואל,
Shmuel, but that he says in order to fear them because it
says you shall place a king that his fear should be upon
you. So that is how רש"י Rashi is reading the exact same
language earlier of לאיימם עליהם, L'ayem aleihem, that he wanted them, if
they're gonna have a king, that they should really be subject, subjugated
to him and really have the fear of the king upon them.
Some I should point out by the way that it's the same
שמואל Shmuel who teaches the famous principle of דינא דמלכותא דינא. Dina
d'malchusa dina. So some want to, you know, the law of the
government is the law. Now here we're talking about a Jewish king
in Israel but still some want to compare that to שמואל's Shmuel's
sort of recognition of the power of government. Okay.
וכן היה רבי יהודה אומר, V'chein haya Rabbi Yehuda omer, the same
way רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says. the king be on the people,
so he said another thing that was related to a king. ג'
מצות נצטוו ישראל בכניסתן לארץ *Gimmel mitzvot nitztavu Yisrael bichnisatan la'aretz*. Three
mitzvot the Jewish people were commanded, the Israelites when they came into
the land, meaning these are collective national מצוות *mitzvot*, so and they
are very much about settling the land and being making your own
autonomy and government and sovereignty and so on. להעמיד להם מלך *Leha'amid
lahem melech*, one is to make a king, ולמחות זרעו של עמלק
Amalek, *ulimchot zaro shel Amalek*, to destroy the seed of Amalek, to
wage that war that's a collective national obligation, ולבנות להם בית הבחירה
*velivnot lahem beit habechirah*, and to build the Temple. Okay, so to
establish the government and the land. You have a government, you have
your enemies are destroyed, the things that represent evil, and you have
the, you know, the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. *Beit HaMikdash*, the center
of worship.
All right, so which is interesting, right? So now you have the
רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* who was saying to make fear them is
emphasizing the importance of a king and the king's fear should be
upon the people, and that's why it was being done. Again, very
much not the thrust of why it was being said in שמואל
*Shmuel*, but here that whole idea of פרשת המלך *parshat hamelech* is
because there's an importance and a מצוה *mitzvah* to have a king,
it's not just an option.
Okay. רבי נהוראי אומר *Rabbi Nehorai omer*, Rabbi Nehorai says, לא נאמרה
פרשה זו אלא כנגד תרעומתן *lo ne'emra parasha zo ela keneged taro'umtan*.
This parsha was only said only because of their complaints, שנאמר ואמרת
אשימה עלי מלך *shene'emar ve'amarta asima alai melech*. So what he is
actually saying is now רש"י *Rashi* says, what's פרשה זו *parasha zo*?
רש"י *Rashi* says שום תשים עליך מלך *som tasim alecha melech* משום
מצוה אלא כנגד תרעומתן *mishum mitzvah ela keneged taro'umtan*. It's not a
mitzvah to have a king. It's some if the people complain and
the people demand it, because it says exactly, you know, ואמרת *ve'amarta*,
you will say that you will want. And this is exactly the
tension both in the פסוקים *psukim* in the תורה *Torah* and in
שמואל *Shmuel* and in ספר שופטים *Sefer Shoftim* is a מלך *melech*
a good thing, not a good thing and so on. So that's
exactly playing out as this debate here between רבי נהוראי *Rabbi Nehorai*
and רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*. You also could have said that כנגד
תרעומתן *keneged taro'umtan* is the פרשת מלך *parshat melech* in שמואל *Shmuel*
that he's saying that in order to get them to change their
mind, but it's the same point. Okay. תניא *Tanya*, it was taught
in a ברייתא *braita*, רבי אליעזר אומר *Rabbi Eliezer omer*, זקנים שבדור
כהוגן שאלו *zkeinim shebador kahogen sha'alu*. Actually, it depends. It could be
that it's a good thing to ask for a king or not
a good thing, but it depends on how you imagine what the
king will do and how you're asking. So the elders of the
generation asked properly, שנאמר תנה לנו מלך לשפטנו *shene'emar tnah lanu melech
lishofteinu*. Give us a king to judge us. You know, we want
somebody to instill justice in the land. You need a strong central
authority, you need to have justice needs to be done. אבל עמי
הארץ שבהן *aval amei ha'aretz shebahen*, but the populace, קלקלו *kilkelu*, they're
the ones that messed it up. They had the wrong concept of
a king, שנאמר והיינו גם אנחנו ככל הגוים ושפטנו מלכנו ויצא לפנינו
*shene'emar vehayinu gam anachnu k'chol hagoyim ushfatanu malkenu veyatza lefanenu*. That he
will be like all the nations, he will judge us and he
will go out in front of us. So which way was this
a קלקול *kilkul*? There are two things that they added. One is
ככל הגוים *k'chol hagoyim*, right? So maybe it's that's what's focusing. Oh
we want to just be like them. We want to be like,
like you know, a nation among nations. So it's that desire that
outside that motivation to be like them and not for the intrinsic
reason, that is maybe what's bad, or maybe it's the ויצא לפנינו
*veyatza lefanenu*. If you look at רש"י *Rashi*, רש"י *Rashi* says עמי
הארץ קלקלו *amei ha'aretz kilkelu*, four lines from the wide lines, דאילו
זקנים שאלו לשופטם ולרדות הסרבנים שבהן *d'ilu zkeinim sha'alu lishoftam u'lirdot hasarvanim
shebahen*, you know to make to to instill justice and use authority
for that. אבל עמי הארץ תלו עליו מלחמות שנאמר ויצא בראשנו ונלחם
את מלחמותינו *aval amei ha'aretz talu alav milchamot shene'emar veyatza beroshenu v'nilcham
et milchamoteinu*. Right, so they wanted, you know, it wasn't just about
the first thing you have to do is you have to care
about the populace and the people and that we should have a
just country and so on. The idea of fighting wars and expansion
and all of that, that should not be what, you know, your
proper sort of focus and motivation should be. Interesting that that's the
part of פסוק רש"י *pasuk Rashi* focuses on. Okay. תניא רבי יוסי
אומר *Tanya Rabbi Yosi omer*, רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi* teaches, this is
the similar as the teaching we just had before of רבי יהודה
*Rabbi Yehuda*, ג' מצות נצטוו ישראל בכניסתן לארץ *Gimmel mitzvot nitztavu Yisrael
bichnisatan la'aretz*. Three mitzvot, להעמיד להם מלך ולכרות זרעו של עמלק ולבנות
להם בית הבחירה *leha'amid lahem melech u'lichrot zaro shel Amalek velivnot lahem
beit habechirah*, ואיני יודע איזה מהם תחילה *ve'eini yode'a eizeh mehem techila*.
So I don't know which one comes first. What is this order?
Why is it specifically this order? So כשהוא אומר כי יד על
כס יה מלחמה לה' בעמלק *kshehu omer ki yad al kes Ya
milchama l'Hashem b'Amalek* because the hand is on the seat of God,
a fight for God against Amalek, הוי אומר להעמיד להם מלך תחילה
*hevei omer leha'amid lahem melech techila*, so it has to start with
a king. Why? ואין כיסא אלא מלך *ve'ein kisei ela melech*, because
כיסא *kisei*, the throne, means a king, שנאמר וישב שלמה Shlomo. על
כיסא ה' למלך *shene'emar vayeshev Shlomo al kisei Hashem lemelech*. Shlomo sat
on the seat of God, on the throne of God. So there's
כס יה *kes Ya*. So it's again the throne of God. So
if you want to wage war against עמלק *Amalek*, you have to
do it with a king. ועדיין איני יודע אם לבנות להם בית
הבחירה תחילה או להכרית זרעו של עמלק תחילה *ve'adayin eini yode'a im
livnot lahem beit habechirah techila o lehachrit zaro shel Amalek techila*. Okay.
Now which comes first? You have a king, but then is it
followed by the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. *Beit HaMikdash* or is it
followed by להכרית זרעו של עמלק *lehachrit zaro shel Amalek* first? Maybe
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, should come even before the king. Anyway, so
how do I know what order that is? כשהוא אומר והניח לכם
מכל אויביכם, K'shehu omer v'heniach lachem mikol oyveichem,
God will give you to rest from all of your enemies, and
then והיה המקום אשר יבחר השם, v'haya hamakom asher yivchar Hashem, הוי
אומר להכרית זרעו של עמלק תחילה. Hevei omer l'hachris zaro shel Amalek
techila. So there you see that first after all of your enemies
are destroyed, then you erect the בית המקדש. And that's exactly of
course what happened. First they elected שאול Shaul as the king, then
God told שאול Shaul to destroy עמלק, and then by the time
of דוד, David, they had the בית המקדש. וכן בדוד הוא אומר,
V'chein b'David hu omer, ויהי כי ישב המלך דוד בביתו והשם הניח
לו מסביב. v'yehi ki yashav hamelech David b'veiso v'Hashem hiniach lo misaviv.
After the king sat and you know his enemies were at peace
after דוד David start whatever דוד David wanted the בית המקדש, it
was built by שלמה. כתיב ויאמר המלך אל נתן הנביא ראה נא
אנכי יושב בבית ארזים. Ksiv vayomer hamelech el Nasan hanavi re'eh na
anochi yoshev b'veis arazim. I am sitting in this house of cedars
and you know the ארון aron is in this you know in
this in this scrawny house and we have to make a house
for God. Okay, so and we will so we will end there
for now and continue this whole discussion about king for tomorrow.